I have a vision for each one of you,
لديّ رؤية لكلّ واحد منكم،
and the vision I have for you
و الرؤية التي لدي لكم
is that when you wake up in the morning,
هي أنك عندما تستيقظ صباحاً
your blood is singing at the thought of being who you are
يغّني دَمك لفكرة كونك من أنت
and doing what you do;
وأنك تفعل ما تفعله؛
that as you go through the day,
وأنك عندما تقضي يومك،
you can literally sink to your knees in gratitude
بإمكانك حرفياً الخوض في الامتنان حتى ركبتيك
at the tremendous good fortune that's been bestowed on you;
شاكراً الحظ السعيد الذي أُنعِم بهِ عليك؛
that as you go through the day,
ذلك أنك عندما تقضي يومك،
you become radiantly alive several times.
فإنك تحس ببهجة كونك حياً لعدد من المرات.
And if your life isn't like that,
وإن لم تكن حياتك كذلك،
I'd like to humbly suggest that you're wasting your life.
فأود أن اقترح بتواضع بأنك تضيّع حياتك.
A life is too short to be wasted.
و الحياة اقصر من أن تُضيَع.
So what I propose to do in the next 17 minutes --
لذا ما سأقدمه لكم خلال ال17 دقيقة القادمة--
I've used up one minute already --
فلقد انقضت دقيقة بالفعل--
is to give you a set of powerful tools
هو إعطاؤكم طقم من الأدوات الفعالة
which can get you started on being there.
التي يمكنها مساعدتكم في البدء بالوصول الى تلك الحياة.
Is that of interest to you?
هل أنتم مهتمون؟
Audience: Yes.
الحضور: نعم.
Srikumar Rao: OK.
سريكومار راو: حسناً.
This is a conference on happiness,
هذا مؤتمر عن السعادة،
but even if it wasn't a conference on happiness,
لكن حتى لو لم يكن كذلك،
would it be right if I said that in some way, shape, fashion or form,
هل يصح القول أنه بطريقة ما، بشكل ما، بأسلوب او هيئة ما،
you're devoting your entire life
أنكم تكرسون حياتكم كلها
to being happy?
لتكونوا سعداء؟
Everything you do -- your job, family, children, relationships, whatever --
كل ما تفعلونه --الوظيفة، العائلة، الاطفال، العلاقات، مهما يكن--
is a quest for happiness.
هو للوصول إلى االسعادة.
Correct?
صحيح؟
I'd like you to think about the following:
آمل ان تفكروا في التالي:
What do you have to get
ما الذي عليك الحصول عليه
in order to be happy?
لتكون سعيداً؟
We're just going to spend a minute on this.
سنستغرق دقيقة واحدة في هذا الأمر.
What do you have to get in order to be happy?
ما الذي عليك الحصول عليه لتكون سعيداً؟
Anybody, quick?
أي أحد، أسرع؟
When I conduct this experiment, a bunch of stuff comes up:
عندما أجري هذه التجربة، ظهرت مجموعة أشياء:
vast wealth, trophy spouse, good health, lots of travel, time, etc, etc, etc.
الثراء الفاحش، الشريك المثالي، الصحة الجيدة، الكثير من السفر، الوقت.. الخ.
Right now, if you were to think about it,
الآن، إن فكرّت بالمسألة،
you probably have a list of, "Here's what I need to get
على الأرجح سيكون لديك قائمة من، "هذا ما يجب الحصول عليه
in order to be happy."
لاكون سعيداً."
I would like you to consider this:
أتمنى أن تفكروا في هذا:
anything that you can get --
أي شيء تستطيعون امتلاكه--
let me repeat that -- anything you can get, you can un-get.
مرة ثانية-- أي شيء تستطيعون امتلاكه، تستطيعون فقدانه
Is that correct?
صحيح؟
So, vast wealth can make you happy. Vast wealth can disappear tomorrow.
الصحة المثالية تجعلك سعيداً. لكنها قد تختفي غداً.
A number of people in the financial sector have discovered this already.
العاملون في القطاع المالي يدركون الأمر جيداً.
So whatever you get that can make you happy
إذن مهما يكن ما تحصل عليه ليجعلك سعيداً
can go away.
قد يختفي في أي لحظة.
Where does that leave you?
أي ستكون عندها؟
Not a very nice place, right?
ستكون في وضع سيء، صحيح؟
I have a different proposition to suggest to you.
لدي مسألة مختلفة اقترحها لكم.
What I have to suggest to you
ما أقترحه هو
is that there is nothing that you have to get, do or be
لا يوجد شيء يجب عليك أن تمتلكه، تفعله، أو تكونه
in order to be happy.
لتكون سعيداً.
Let me repeat that:
دعني أكرر ذلك:
there is nothing that you have to get, do or be in order to be happy.
لا يوجد شيء يجب عليك أن تمتلكه، تفعله، أو تكونه لتكون سعيداً.
In fact, happiness is your innate nature.
في الحقيقة، السعادة هي طبيعتك الذاتية.
It is hardwired into you. It is part of your DNA.
إنها مثبّتة فيك. هي جزء من حمضك النووي.
You cannot not be happy.
لا تستطيع أن تكون غير سعيد.
Now, all of you are very polite,
الآن، جميعكم مؤدبون جداً،
and in some of the other forums I speak in, such as top business schools,
في بعض المنتديات الأخرى التي اتحدث فيها مثل كليات الأعمال الراقية،
they're not so polite.
ليس الجمهور بهذا الأدب.
And invariably, somebody articulates what many of you are thinking,
وفي كل مرة، ينطق شخص ما ما يفكر فيه الكثير منكم،
which is: "If happiness is my innate nature,
وهو: "إذا كانت السعادة طبيعتي الذاتية
how come I am not experiencing it?
لم لا أشعر بها إذن؟
How come I am experiencing my life sucks?"
لمَ أشعر بان حياتي رهيبة؟"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And the answer to that is actually very simple.
وفي الحقيقة، الإجابة على ذلك بسيطة جدا.
You have spent your entire life
لقد قضيتم حياتكم كلّها
learning to be unhappy.
تتعلمون كيف تكونون تعساء.
Let me repeat that: you have spent your entire life learning to be unhappy.
سأكرر: لقد قضيتم حياتكم تتعلمون كيف تكونون تعساء.
And the way we learn to be unhappy
وطريقة تعلمنا أن نكون تعساء
is by buying into a particular mental model.
هي من خلال تصديقنا نموذجاً عقلياً معيّنا.
A mental model is a notion we have that this is the way the world works.
والنموذج العقلي هو مفهومنا عن كيفية سير العالم.
All of us have mental models, we've got dozens of mental models.
كلنا لدينا نماذج عقلية، لدينا العشرات من النماذج العقلية.
We've got mental models on how to find a job,
لدينا نماذج عقلية عن كيفية الحصول على وظيفة،
how to get ahead at work, how to pick a restaurant to eat at,
كيف نرتقي في العمل، كيف نختار مطعما لناكل فيه،
how to have a movie to go to ... dozens of them.
كيف نجد فيلماً لمشاهدته.. العشرات من النماذج.
The problem isn't that we have mental models.
ليست المشكلة في امتلاكنا لنماذج عقلية.
The problem is that we don't know
المشكلة أننا لا نعرف أنّ لدينا نماذج عقلية.
We think this is the way the world works.
نظن أن هذه طريقة سيرالعالم.
And the more we invest in a mental model,
و كلما استثمرنا في نموذج عقلي،
the more it appears that this, in fact, is the way the world works.
كلما بدا لنا أنها، في الحقيقة، طريقة سير العالم.
But it isn't: it's just a mental model,
لكنها ليست كذلك: إنها نموذج عقلي فحسب،
and the mental model we have that we buy into so strongly
والنموذج العقلي الذي لدينا، والذي نؤمن به بقوة
is that we have to get something so we can do something
هو أننا علينا الحصول على شيء، ليكون باستطاعتنا فعل شيء،
so we can be something.
ليكون باستطاعتنا أن نكون شيئا.
Like, we have to get a great deal of money so we can travel to exotic places
مثل، أن علينا الحصول على كمية كبيرة من المال لنستطيع السفر الى أماكن مذهلة،
so we can be happy.
لنستطيع أن نكون سعداء.
We have to be in a relationship so we can have great sex
علينا أن نكون في علاقة لنستطيع ممارسة جنس رائعة،
so we can be happy.
لنستطيع أن نكون سعداء.
All of this is a variation of the if-then model.
كل ذلك تنوعات من نموذج "إذا-فعندها".
And the if-then model is:
ونموذج"إذا-فعندها" هو:
if this happens,
إذا حدث هذا،
then we will be happy.
فعندها سنكون سعداء.
If I were to get a better job, if I were to get more money,
إذا أمكنني الحصول على وظيفة أفضل إذا امتلكت مالاً أكثر
if my boss would have a heart attack,
إذا حدثت لمديري سكتة قلبية،
if only I was married, if only my wife would leave me --
إذا تزوجت، إذا تركتني زوجتي--
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
if only I had children,
إذا كان لدي أطفال،
if my children would grow up and go to college ...
إذا كبر أولادي و ذهبوا للجامعة..
It doesn't matter what it is.
لا يهم ما هو.
The whole notion is if this happens,
الفكرة كلها هي إذا حدث هذا،
then I will be happy.
فعندها سأكون سعيداً.
And right now, the only thing that's different
وفي الوقت الحالي، الأمر الوحيد المختلف
between the persons in this audience
بين الأشخاص في هذا الجمهور
is what is the particular "if" that you are focusing on?
هو ما هي الـ"إذا" التي تركزون عليها؟
And the only thing that's different
والأمر الوحيد المختلف
between you now and where you were 10 years ago
بينك الآن وبينك قبل 10 أعوام
is what is the particular "if" that you were focusing on?
هو ما هي الـ "إذا" التي كنت تركز عليها؟
Think about your life 10 years ago.
فكروا بحياتكم قبل 10 أعوام.
Spend a minute doing that.
اقضوا دقيقة في فعل ذلك.
Ten years ago, if you remember clearly,
قبل 10 أعوام، إن كنتم تذكرون بوضوح،
there were certain things you wanted.
كانت هنالك أمورمعينة أردتموها.
Is that correct?
هل ذلك صحيح؟
Odds are pretty good
والإحتمال الأكبر
that many of those things you wanted 10 years ago you now have.
أنّ كثيرا من الأشياء التي أردتموها قبل 10 أعوام تمتلكونها الآن.
Is that correct?
هل ذلك صحيح؟
Where has that left you?
أين يترككم ذلك؟
In exactly the same place, right?
في نفس الوضع بالضبط، صحيح؟
What we don't realize is the model itself is flawed.
إنّ ما لا ندركه هو أنّ النموذج نفسه خاطئ.
The if-then model -- "If this happens I will be happy" --
نموذج إذا-فعندها -- "إذا حصل هذا فعندها سأكون سعيداً"--
the model itself is flawed.
النموذج نفسه خاطئ.
But instead of recognizing that it is the model itself that's flawed,
ولكن بدل تمييز أنّ النموذج نفسه خاطئ،
what we do is spend enormous amounts of time
نقوم بقضاء كم هائل من الوقت
changing the "if."
في تغيير الـ "إذا".
"Oh, well, I thought if I became CEO it would help,
"آه، حسناً، ظننتُ أنني إذا أصبحت مديراً تنفيذياً سيساعدني ذلك،
but now I realize it's not that I want to become a CEO.
ولكني الآن أدرك أنني لا أريد أن أصبح مديراً تنفيذيا.
I want to become the billionaire CEO,
فأنا أريد أن اصبح مديراً تنفيذياً مليارديراً،
and then I will be happy."
فعندها سأكون سعيداً."
You've got your own variation on that.
لدى كل واحد منكم رؤية خاصة به لذلك الأمر.
But it's the model itself that's flawed, not what you put on the "if" side
ولكنّ النموذج نفسه خاطئ، وليس ما تضعونه على جانب "إذا"
of the equation.
من المعادلة.
I can demonstrate that to you.
بإمكاني توضيح ذلك لكم.
Can any of you recall a time
هل باستطاعة أيّ منكم تذكّر مرة
when you were confronted with a scene of such spectacular beauty
كنتم فيها أمام منظر ذي جمال خلاب
that it took you outside of yourself into a place of great serenity?
بحيث أخذكم جماله إلى خارج أنفسكم الى مكان تملؤه السكينة؟
Maybe a rainbow, a mountain range,
ربما قوس قزح، سلسلة جبلية،
a valley, the sea.
واد، أو بحر.
And if you remember that -- raise your hands if you could.
وإن كنتم تتذكرون أمراً كذلك-- هلا رفعتم أيديكم.
Virtually all of you could, right?
يتذكر جميعكم أمراً كذلك، صحيح؟
Have you ever wondered why that happened?
هل تساءلتم مرةً لماذا حدث ذلك؟
The reason that happened is that somehow,
إنّ سبب حدوث ذلك هو أنكم بشكل ما،
for some reason,
لسبب ما،
at that instant,
في ذلك الوقت،
you accepted the universe exactly as it was.
قبلتم الكون كما هو تماماً.
You didn't say,
لم تقولوا،
"That's a beautiful rainbow, but it's kind of off to the left,
"إنه قوس قزح جميل، لكنه يميل إلى اليسار قليلا،
and if I could move it 200 yards to the right,
ولو استطعت تحريكه 200 ياردة إلى اليمين،
it would be ever so much more beautiful."
سيكون أجمل من ذلك بكثير."
(Laughter)
(َضحك)
You didn't say, "That's a beautiful valley,
لم تقولوا، "ذلك واد جميل،
but the tree in the foreground has too many crooked branches.
ولكنّ الشجرة أمامه فيها أغصان كثيرة منحنية.
So if you gave me a chainsaw and 20 minutes,
فلو أعطيتني منشاراً كهربائياً و20 دقيقة،
I'd make it ever so much better."
لأمكنني جعله أفضل بكثير."
Oh no, the rainbow off-center
آه كلا، قوس القزح المائل عن الوسط
was just fine.
كان جيداً فحسب.
The tree with its crooked branches
الشجرة بأغصانها المنحنية
And the moment you accepted the universe just as it was,
وفي اللحظة التي قبلتم فيها الكون كما هو تماماً،
your habitual-wanting self dropped away,
ذهبت عنكم نفسكم المتطلبة بالعادة،
and the happiness which is your innate nature surfaced,
وعلت السعادة التي هي طبيعتكم الذاتية،
and you felt it.
فشعرتم بها.
And I know you felt it because now,
وأعرف أنكم شعرتم بها لأنكم الآن،
even now after all those years,
حتى بعد مرور كل تلك الأعوام،
you can still remember it.
لا يزال بإمكانهم تذكرها.
The problem is that your life right now,
المشكلة أنّ حياتكم الآن،
with all of the problems that you have --
مع جميع المشاكل التي تواجهكم--
more precisely, all of the problems that you think you have --
بدقة أكبر، جميع المشاكل التي تظنون أنها تواجهكم--
is equally perfect.
مثالية كما كانت.
But you do not accept it.
ولكنكم لا تقبلونها.
In fact, you're spending all your time
في الحقيقة، أنكم تقضون كل وقتكم
striving with might and main to make it different.
تكافحون بكل ما أوتيتم من قوة لجعلها مختلفة.
You are not accepting it.
فأنتم لا تقبلونها.
And when you're not accepting it,
وعندما لا تقبلونها،
you're buying into the if-then model:
فإنكم تؤمنون بنموذج إذا-فعندها:
if this happens, then I will be happy.
إذا حدث هذا، فعندها أكون سعيداً.
And it's the model itself that is flawed.
والنموذج نفسه خاطئ.
So let me show you how you can get out of that,
لذا دعوني أريكم كيف يمكنكم التخلص من ذلك،
or at least you can begin the steps towards getting out of that.
أو عالأقل يمكنكم بدء الخطوات تجاه التخلص من ذلك.
I'd like to share with you that action.
أوَدّ أن اشارككم ذلك الحدث.
We all live our lives because we want to achieve something, correct?
كلنا نعيش حياتنا لأننا نريد الوصول إلى شيء ما، صحيح؟
You know, we are here and we want to have something.
كما تعرفون، نحن هنا ونريد أن نمتلك شيئاً ما.
Alex wants to have a successful conference.
أليكس يريد أن ينجح المؤتمر.
You know, many of you want to have great programs for your companies
كما تعرفون، العديد منكم يريد أن يكون لديه برنامج لشركته
that are very successful.
يكون ناجحاً جداً.
You want to progress, have more money, all of that, is that correct?
تريدون أن تتقدموا، تحصلوا على المزيد من المال، كل ذلك، هل ذلك صحيح؟
Each of those is an outcome; you would like something to happen.
كل واحد من تلك الأمور نتيجة؛ ترغب في أن يحصل شيء ما.
Now, I'd like you to think about the following:
الآن، هلّا فكرتم بالتالي:
actions are within your control,
الأفعال تحت سيطرتنا،
not entirely, but to a large extent.
ليس تماماً، ولكن إلى مدى بعيد.
The outcome is completely out of your control.
ولكن النتيجة خارجة عن سيطرتنا بالكلية.
OK?
جيد؟
Actions are within your control.
الأفعال تحت سيطرتكم.
The outcome is completely outside your control.
النتائج خارج سيطرتكم بصورة كاملة.
Have any of you recognized that when you have a goal
هل أدرك أيّ منكم أنه عندما يكون لديه هدف
and you start to work towards it,
ويشرع في العمل لتحقيقه،
some of the time you don't achieve your goal,
أنه في بعض الأحيان، لا يحقق ذلك الهدف،
and some of the time what you get
وفي أحيان أخرى، يكون ما يحصل عليه
is the exact opposite of what you wanted?
نقيض ما أراده بالضبط؟
Has that happened to any of you?
هل حدث ذلك لأي منكم؟
Like there was a friend of mine who said, "Gee, you know,
مثال ذلك قال صديق لي، "اوه، أتعلم،
I have not been paying a lot of attention to my wife,
لم أكن أولي الكثير من الانتباه لزوجتي،
and this has to change."
ويجب أن يتغير ذلك."
So the next time we went on a business trip,
لذا في المرة اللاحقة التي ذهبنا في رحلة عمل،
he bought a very expensive dress for her.
اشترى فستاناً باهظاً لها.
And this was his way of showing, you know, I care for you,
وهذه كانت طريقته في إظهار، كما تعرفون، أهتمّ بكِ،
and nice things would happen.
والأمور الحسنة ستحصل.
And when he presented the gift to his wife, her immediate reaction was,
وعندما قدّم الهدية لزوجته، كان رد فعلها المباشر،
"After 20 years of marriage, you don't know my size?"
"بعد 20 عاماً من زواجنا، لا زلت لا تعلم مقاسي؟"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
"And furthermore, don't you know I never wear this kind of thing?"
"وعلاوة على ذلك، ألا تعرف أني لا أرتدي أبداً مثل هذا النوع؟"
And the next thing you know, he had a full-blown marital spat.
ومن حيث لا يدري، كان أمام شجار عائلي كبير
Has that happened to any of you?
هل حدث ذلك لأي منكم؟
You've taken action for a particular outcome
قمتم بفعل لأجل نتيجة معينة
and the outcome you got was the exact opposite
وكانت النتيجة التي حصلتم عليها تماماً عكس
of what you wanted?
ما أردتم؟
Happens all the time.
يحدث ذلك دوماً.
Well, we live in a world where what we think of,
حسناً، نعيش في عالم حيث يكون ما نفكر فيه،
what we invest in,
ما نستثمر فيه،
is the outcome.
هو النتيجة.
We define our life in the following way:
نعرّف حياتنا بالطريقة التالية:
here I am, here is where I want to go,
ها أنا ذا، هناك حيث أريد الذهاب،
these are the steps I have to take in order to get from where I am
هذه هي الخطوات التي عليّ اتخاذها لكي أنتقل من حيث أنا
to where I want to go,
إلى حيث أريد الذهاب،
and if I succeed, life is wonderful.
فإن نجحت، فالحياة رائعة.
And if I don't, then I have failed,
وإن لم أنجح، أكون عندها قد فشلت،
life is no good, life sucks.
ليست الحياة صالحة، الحياة رديئة.
True? False?
صحيح؟ خطأ؟
That is how we live.
هكذا نحيا.
We invest in the outcome,
إننا نستثمر في النتائج،
and as I've just pointed out,
وكما أشرتُ توّاً،
the outcome is frequently different from what we would like,
فإنّ النتيجة تختلف عادة عمّا نحب أن تكون،
and sometimes the diametric opposite of what we would like.
وفي بعض الأحيان تكون عكساً مضاداً لما نحب.
You invest in the outcome and you are guaranteed to have
استثمر في النتائج وأضمن لك الحصول
more than your share of frustration, angst
على أكثر من نصيبك من الإحباط، والقلق
and all the rest of the stuff that makes life suck.
وبقية الأمور التي تجعل الحياة رديئة.
There is an alternative.
هنالك بديل.
And the alternative is that you do not invest in the outcome,
والبديل هو ألا تستثمر في النتائج،
you invest in the process.
بل بالعملية نفسها.
And the best way to describe that is a quote by John Wooden.
وأفضل طريقة لوصف ذلك هي اقتباس لجون وودِن.
I don't know how many of you are familiar with John Wooden.
لا أعلم كم منكم يعرفون جون وودِن.
He's very well-known in the United States
إنه مشهور جداُ في الولايات المتحدة
and certainly among basketball fans.
بالتأكيد عند جماهير كرة السلة.
He's the only person ever to make the basketball Hall of Fame
هو الشخص الوحيد الذي وصل إلى قاعة مشاهير كرة السلة
both as a player and as a coach.
كلاعب وكمدرّب أيضاً.
And what he told his entering team --
وكان ما قاله لفريقه--
he led UCLA to an unprecedented number of victories and finals in the NCAA --
قاد فريق جامعة كاليفورنيا، لوس أنجلوس لعدد غير مسبوق من الانتصارات والنهائيات في NCAA
and what he used to tell any new team is he never spoke about winning.
-- وكان ما يقوله لأي فريق جديد هو أنه لم يتحدث أبداً عن الفوز.
He always said, "When it's over and you look in the mirror,
كان يقول دائماً، "عندما تنتهي المباراة وتنظر في المرآة،
did you do the best that you were capable of?
هل فعلت كلّ ما أنت قادر عليه؟
And if you did the best that you were capable of,
فإن كنت قد فعلت ما باستطاعتك،
the score doesn't matter.
فالنتيجة ليست مهمة.
But I would suspect that if you did the best that you were capable of,
ولكنّي أظن بأنك لو فعلت أحسن ما باستطاعتك،
you will find the score to your liking."
لوجدت النتيجة كما تحبها."
That is investing in a process.
هذا استثمار في العملية.
What we do is the exact opposite.
ما نفعله هو العكس تماماً.
We invest in the outcome.
فنحن نستثمر في النتائج.
This is what I want -- oh, I want it so desperately,
هذا ما أريد-- آه، أريده بشدّة،
because if I get it I will be happy.
لأني إن حصلت عليه سأكون سعيداً.
And you try with might and main, to do whatever you can,
وتحاول بكل ما أوتيتَ من قوة، أن تفعل كل ما تقدِر عليه،
but you are always focusing on, "This is the outcome."
ولكنّك تركز دائما على، "هذه هي النتيجة."
Now, focusing on the outcome is fine.
حسناً، لا بأس في التركيز على النتائج.
It gives you direction.
فذلك يرشدك إلى الوجهة.
Investing in the outcome means
الاستثمار في النتائج يعني
that you make the achievement of a particular outcome
أنك تجعل من الوصول إلى نتيجة معينة
dependent for your well-being.
ركيزة لسعادتك.
And that is a surefire recipe for failure.
وتلك وصفة أكيدة للفشل.
What you can do is something else.
إنّ ما يمكنكم فعله شيئاً آخر.
You can invest in the process.
يمكنكم الاستثمار في العملية.
That is, once you have determined, here is where I am,
بحيث، عندما تقررون، أنا الآن هنا،
here is where I want to be, and that's fine,
وأريد أن أكون هناك، ولا بأس في ذلك،
you focus on the outcome only to the extent that it gives you direction,
فأنتم تركزون على النتيجة فقط إلى حد تعطيكم فيه الاتجاهات،
and then you invest yourself completely in the process.
وثمّ تستثمرون أنفسكم كلياً في العملية.
You say, here are the steps you want to take,
فتقولون، هذه هي الخطوات التي نريد اتباعها،
and you put everything into it.
وتستثمرون كلّ شيء فيها.
And if you succeed, wonderful.
فإن نجحتم، ذلك رائع.
And if you don't succeed,
وإن لم تنجحوا،
still wonderful,
ذلك أيضاً رائع،
because now you have a new starting point, and from that new starting point,
لأنكم الآن لديكم نقطة بداية جديدة، ومن نقطة البداية تلك،
you select another outcome and keep going.
تختارون نتيجة أخرى وتواصلون العمل.
And when you do that, you will find that every day is a blast.
وعندما تقومون بذلك، سترَون أنّ كلّ يوم بمثابة احتفال.
Let me give you an example.
دعوني أعطيكم مثالاً.
And if you have children -- raise your hands if you have children.
إن كان لديكم أولاد-- أرفعوا ايديكم إن كان لديكم أولاد.
Have you ever seen a small child learn to walk?
هل رأيتم طفلاً صغيراً يتعلم المشي؟
What happens, and this happens typically between 11 and 13 months,
الذي يحصل، وذلك يحصل عادة بين 11 و 13 شهرا من العمر،
is the child gets up and she sees everybody walking,
هو أنّ الطفل يقوم ويرى الجميع يمشون،
she wants to walk, she gets up, she falls down, she starts crying
فيريد المشي، يقوم، ويقع، ويبدأ البكاء
and momma runs up and comforts her, kisses the place, makes it well.
وتركض الأم لمواساته، وتقبّل مكان السقوط، فتُشعره بتحسن.
She tries again, falls down, mommy runs up again.
يحاول الطفل مرة أخرى، يقع أرضاً، وتركض الأم مرة أخرى.
After some time, mommy feels tired and no longer runs up
وبعد بعض الوقت، تشعر الأم بالتعب ولا تعاود الركض إلى الطفل
and the child stops crying,
ويتوقف الطفل عن البكاء،
and then she gets up, takes a step
ثمّ ينهض، ويمشي خطوة
and doesn't fall down, and then she takes another,
ولا يقع أرضاً، ثمّ يمشي خطوة أخرى،
and a beautiful smile comes on her face.
وتعلو وجهه ابتسامة جميلة.
And very soon, generally within 24 hours, she's walking all over the place,
وبعد ذلك بقليل، عموما خلال 24 ساعة، يكون الطفل يمشي في الأنحاء،
upsetting your living room arrangements.
ويبعثر ترتيب غرفة المعيشة.
And you know you've gone to a new stage of parenting.
وتعلم أنّك انتقلت إلى مرحلة جديدة من العناية بالطفل.
Right?
صحيح؟
Now, imagine what would happen
الآن، تخيّلوا ما كان ليحدث
if each time the child fell,
لو أنّ كل مرة وقع فيها الطفل،
she would say, "Oh my God, I failed again.
قال، "يا الهي، لقد فشلتُ مرة أخرى.
I'm never going to learn to walk."
لن أتعلم المشي أبداً."
And you have to get counseling for her
ويكون عليكم أن تجلبوا له المساعدة
to help her deal with feelings of inadequacy
ليستطيع التعامل مع مشاعر عدم الكفاءة
and not being able to achieve and fail yet again.
وعدم القدرة على الوصول والفشل في كل مرة.
How long do you think it would take her to learn to walk if you had to do that,
كم برأيكم سيستغرق الطفل لتعلم المشي إن كان عليه فعل ذلك،
if every three times she fell down, you had to get a counselor
إن كان عليكم جلب المساعدة بعد كل ثلاث مرات يقع فيها
to counsel her and so on?
لمواساته وغير ذلك؟
Sounds funny, doesn't it?
يبدو الأمر مضحكاً، أليس كذلك؟
But that is exactly what we're doing.
ولكن ذلك ما نفعله بالضبط.
What the child is doing is focusing on the process.
إنّ ما يفعله الطفل هو التركيز على العملية.
She's investing in the process,
إنه يستثمر في العملية،
not in the outcome.
وليس في النتيجة.
What we do is the exact opposite.
وما نفعله نحن هو العكس تماماً.
As we grow up, we lose the ability to invest in the process,
فيما نتقدم في العمر، نفقد القدرة على الاستثمار في العملية،
we start investing in the outcome.
ونبدأ الاستثمار في النتائج.
By definition the outcome is outside of our control,
والنتائج بطبيعتها خارج سيطرتنا،
and if that's where we spend all of our emotional energy,
وإن كان ذلك حيث ننفق كلّ طاقتنا العاطفية،
we are going to get drained as we do.
فإننا سنستنفدها في سعينا.
But if, on the other hand, we said,
من ناحية أخرى، إذا قلنا،
"Here is the outcome, I am going to invest in the process
"هذه هي النتيجة، وسأقوم بالاستثمار في العملية
and give it every single bit I could,"
وسأبذل لأجلها كل ما أستطيع،"
every day is a blast,
فسيكون كلّ يوم رائعاً،
and you're well on your way to achieving the vision that I outlined to you.
وستكونون في مساركم إلى تحقيق الرؤية التي حددتها لكم.
The question that I get all the time, is people say, "Professor Rao,
السؤال الذي أتلقاه دائما، يقول الناس، "بروفيسور راو،
but nothing makes me passionate."
ولكن لا شيء يجعلني شغوفاً."
So I say, "OK, what would?"
فأقول،"حسناً،ما الذي سيجعلك كذلك؟"
And they invariably come up with, you know, here is a list of things.
ويجيب الجميع بأن يقدموا قائمة أشياء.
Here's my job and here's how much it pays,
هذا عملي وهذا ما يعود عليّ به،
this is the kind of person my boss is,
ورئيسي من هذا النوع من الناس،
the kind of people my colleagues are,
وزملائي من ذلك النوع من الناس،
and here's how my customers are, here's how much I travel,
وهذا ما عليه زبائني، وهذا مقدار ما أسافره،
here's how big my office is, how deep the carpeting is,
وهذا حجم مكتبي، وهذه وثرة سجادتي،
how many windows I have --
وعدد نوافذي--
a bunch of parameters.
عدد من المؤشرات.
And what I tell them is what I want to share with you,
وما أخبرهم به هو ما أريد مشاركته معكم،
because all of that stuff -- first of all, it doesn't exist.
لأن كل ذلك-- أولاً، ليس له وجود.
But second, even if it did and you were plugged into it,
وثانيا، حتى لوكان موجوداً وكنتم مشدودين اإليه،
it would not take more than six months
لن يستغرق أكثر من ستة أشهر
for you to be the same sorry, miserable self there as you are now,
لتشعروا بنفس الأسى، والتعاسة التي تشعرون بها الآن،
because passion exists inside you.
لأن الشغف موجود في داخلكم.
It does not exist in the job.
ولا يوجد في العمل.
And if you don't find a way to ignite it within you
وإن لم تجدوا طريقة لإشعاله في داخلكم
right where you are,
حيثما أنتم،
you are not going to find it outside.
فلن تجدوه في الخارج.
But if you do find a way to ignite it where you are,
ولكن إن وجدتم طريقة لإشعاله حيث أنتم،
then you will find that the external world
فعندها ستجدون أنّ العالم الخارجي
rearranges itself
سيعيد ترتيب نفسه
to accommodate the new person that you are becoming.
ليناسب الإنسان الجديد الذي أصبحتموه.
And as you do that, you will find that miracles happen on a regular basis.
وفيما تفعلون ذلك، ستجدون أن المعجزات ستحدث بصورة اعتيادية.
Persons come up whom you're delighted to meet.
ستجدون أشخاصاً يسركم لقاؤهم.
New people enter your life.
أشخاص جدد سيدخلون حياتكم.
It's just a breeze,
ويكون ذلك سهلا كالنسيم،
because all you do in your life is you take journeys.
لأن كل ما تفعلونه في حياتكم هو رحلة.
You came here to this conference; you went on a journey.
عندما أتيتم إلى هذا المؤتمر؛ قمتم برحلة.
You hang around the water cooler,
عندما تقفون بجانب مبردة الماء،
talking about how terrible your place of work is;
تتحدثون عن مدى بشاعة محل عملكم؛
you went on a journey.
فأنتم تقومون برحلة.
You watch "Desperate Housewives," you go on a journey.
عندما تشاهدون مسلسل "ربات بيوت يائسات"
You go on a journey
تقومون برحلة
where 40-something women are having affairs with 19-something gardeners
حيث تقيم نساء تجاوزن سنّ الأربعين علاقات مع بستانيين شبان في سن 19
while the husbands are playing around with models.
فيما يكون الأزواج يعبثون مع عارضات أزياء.
All you do is go on journeys.
كلّ ما تفعلونه هو قيام برحلات.
There's nothing wrong with that, but just ask yourself,
ولا عيبَ في ذلك، ولكن اسألوا أنفسكم،
"Is this a journey I want to take?
"هل هذه هي الرحلة التي أودّ القيام بها؟
Does this take me to a place I want to spend time?"
هل تأخذني الى مكان أريد قضاء الوقت فيه؟"
And if you start doing that,
وإن بدأتم فعل ذلك،
you will find that your life changes.
سترونَ أن حياتكم تتغير.
The kind of people you meet, the things you talk about,
نوع الناس الذين تلتقون بهم، الأشياء التي تتحدثون عنها،
the movies you go to, the books you read --
الأفلام التي تشاهدونها، وحتى الكتب--
everything changes.
كل ذلك يتغير.
And you begin all of that
وتبدأون كل ذلك
by focusing on the process.
عن طريق التركيز على العملية.
Invest in the process, not in the outcome.
استثمروا في العملية، و ليس النتائج.
Thank you.
شكراً لكم.